<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Resurgendum. A notable sermon concerning the resurrection, preached not long since at the court, by L. S.</title>
            <author>L. S., fl. 1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120772</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855966</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855966</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11247)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1530:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Resurgendum. A notable sermon concerning the resurrection, preached not long since at the court, by L. S.</title>
                  <author>L. S., fl. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [R. Field for] Iohn VVolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21478:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21478:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>RESVRGENDVM.</p>
            <p>A NOTABLE SERMON CONCERNING THE RESVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, preached not long ſince at the Court, by L. S.</p>
            <p>
               <q>We haue here no continuing Citie; but we ſeeke one to come.
<bibl>Hebr. chap. 13. verſe 14.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <q>Reſurget iuſtus, vt iudicet: peccator, vt iudicetur: impius, vt ſine iudicio puniatur.</q>
            <figure>
               <head>IW</head>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Wolfe</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn VVolfe. 1593.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21478:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21478:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Send thee here (gentle Reader) a Sermon, for ſtile eloquent, for order methodicall, and for ſubſtance of matter, right heauenly: heartily praying thee (euen for thine ovvne ſoules health) to vouchſafe the reading thereof. Taken it vvas not from the Preachers mouth by any fond or nevv found Characteriſme (vvhich to the great preiudice of ſome vvorthie and learned men, hath of late verie piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blemished ſome part of their labours this vvay, vvith intollerable mutilations): but ſet dovvne at their deſire, vvho might herein command, by the Authors ovvne pen: and indited (as I verily perſuade my ſelf) by ſpecial inſtinct of the holy Ghoſt. And ſurely the doctrine of this Sermon is ſuch, as I make no doubt at all, but it vvil be held to be moſt needfull and neceſſarie, eſpecially for theſe deſperat times of ours: vvherein amongſt other moſt erronious ſects vvhich rent in peeces the coate of Chriſt, and the vnitie of his Church, that one of the Saduces (vvho ſay there is no reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) is not perhaps of all other the leaſt imbraced. VVith this ſort of hel-hounds this godly Sermon (though not of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) doth chiefly encounter, and vvith inuincible argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts beateth them dovvne flat to the ground: aſſuring all flesh of that great and generall Reſurrection, vvhich euery true Chriſtian is bound both in heart to beleeue, and vvith his mouth to confeſſe: hovvſoeuer the prophane Atheiſt in the
<pb facs="tcp:21478:3"/>
greatneſſe of his vaine and vvicked imaginations may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thervviſe fancie to himſelfe, not vvithout his ovvne reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe damnation, vnleſſe in time he do repent him of his ſinne. And vvould to God many ſuch <hi>alarums</hi> as this, might dayly be rong and ſounded into our eares: that (if it vvere poſsible) euery Chriſtian might haue as deepe an impreſsion, and be no leſſe affected vvith the continuall cogitation and remembrance of our <hi>reſurrection</hi> at the laſt day, then that godly father <hi>S. Ierome</hi> ſeemed to be, vvho ſayd, <hi>Whether I eate or drinke, whether I ſleepe or wake, or what thing elſe ſo euer I do: me thinkes I heare a trumpet alwayes ſounding thus in mine eares: Ariſe you dead, and come vnto iudgement.</hi> And ſo (gentle Reader) I leaue thee to the grace of God.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21478:3"/>
            <head>A NOTABLE SERMON CONCERNING THE RESVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, preached not long ſince at the Court by L. S.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Philip. 3.20.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>20</hi> But our conuerſation is in heauen, from vvhence alſo vve looke for the Sauiour, euen the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>21</hi> VVho shall change our vile bodie, that it may be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shioned like vnto his glorious bodie, according to the vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vvhereby he is able euen to ſubdue all things vnto him ſelfe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe teachers of Gods truth, whoſe works be not anſwerable to the word, are fitly compared to Mercuries, the images in the ſtreetes, which point the right way to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, but ſtand ſtill and walke not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues: or to the ſtage player, who ſpeaking of the earth, pointed to heauen, and meaning the heauen, pointed to the earth, <hi>&amp; manu commiſit ſoloeciſmum.</hi> Such haue the voyce of Iacob but the hands of Eſau: of ſuch the Apoſtle with teares exhorteth the Philippians to beware: in the 18. verſe of the third chapter. And that they may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be knowen, he ſetteth downe their properties, and painteth them out in their colours: as that they be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21478:4"/>
to the croſſe of Chriſt, their bellie is their God, they glorie in their ſhame, they are earthly minded.</p>
            <p>But ſuch as build with both hands the church of God, that is, by ſound doctrine and holy life: ſuch as haue <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> brightneſſe of knowledge and integritie of conuerſation: ſuch as go armed before their brethren, as <hi>Ruben</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi> and halfe <hi>Manaſſes</hi> did, not to be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with errour in faith or deformitie in life: theſe be good guides to folow, and ſure loade ſtarres to direct our courſe. Amongſt which Paule with a good conſcience placeth him ſelfe and ſuch as be like him: ſetting downe in this place their conuerſation to be heauenly. And good cauſe why: for that there is their Sauiour, and that thence they long for him: whoſe comming ſhall not be fruteleſſe to them: for he ſhall chaunge their bodies from ſuch baſe infirmitie as now they are in, to ſuch glorie as his body is clothed withall. Which may not be thought incredible, becauſe his will and power which ſubdueth all things, ſhall bring this to paſſe.</p>
            <p>In the farther vnfolding of which words the Apoſtle putteth in my hands theſe two principall things to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnto you. Firſt, the change that is in the ſoules of the godly in this life. Secondly the change that ſhalbe in their bodies after this life.</p>
            <p>In the former there be theſe points to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled,
<list>
                  <item>That their conuerſation is not earthly but in heauen.</item>
                  <item>The cauſe that draweth them thither, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>A longing and expectation of his comming.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21478:4"/>In the change that ſhalbe of the bodie we are to conſider
<list>
                  <item>What our bodies are nowe. They are vile.</item>
                  <item>What they ſhall be then. Like the glorious bodie of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>The cauſes which bring this to paſſe. The will of God, and his mightie power.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the ioynts and parts of this preſent Scripture, whereof I will ſpeake as the time ſhall permit me: your Honorable patience heare me: the Apoſtle direct me; and God ſhall aſſiſt me with his grace.</p>
            <p>Saint Auguſtine parteth all the people in the world into two companies: the ſynagogue of Sathan, and the Church of God: into Babylon and Ieruſalem: into the ſonnes of the earth, and the Citizens of heauen. In which now are all the godly hauing their conuerſation in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: that is, behauing them ſelues as free Burgeſſes of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem which is aboue.</p>
            <p>Manie Cities in the world haue lawes and cuſtomes differing one from another, yet not ſo contrarie, but one may enioy freedome of diuerſe at once. But heauen and earth haue ſo continuall and ſo vnreconcileable variance as no peace can be compounded betweene them. For he that is free to the one, muſt be disfranchized in the other: he that is friend to the one, muſt be foe to the other: he that hath giuen his faith to the one, muſt ſweare againſt the other. It is as poſſible for light to agree with darknes, for life to be friends with death, for the Arke of God and the idol Dagon to lodge quietly in one place, as for a man to ſerue God and Mammon: to be true to the Lord and the world: to be free Deniſon beneath and aboue, to haue an earthly and a heauenly conuerſation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21478:5"/>Therefore Elias doth ſharply reproue the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell for halting betweene two opinions, in following the Lord, and going after Baall. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18.21.</p>
            <p>The Samaritans for feare of Lyons which deuoured them, had a Prieſt ſent vnto them to teach them the true ſeruice of God, yet withall they retained their old ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and affection to their natiue Idolles, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Mungrelles in religion, neither faithfull worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the true God, nor kinde followers of their falſe gods. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17.33.</p>
            <p>Naman the Syrian, after he was cleanſed of his lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, made a vowe to offer incenſe or ſacrifice to none but vnto the Lord: yet he will needes go with his Maiſter into the houſe of Rimmon, whereby he may keepe the kings fauour, keepe his authoritie, continue his honour, enioy his wealth, and this is to ſeeke to reconcile heauen and earth together. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.18.</p>
            <p>Nicodemus his caſe was much like, who would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a Diſciple of Chriſt, yet commeth to him by night, that he might not looſe his credit of the world. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.10. There came a young man to Chriſt, verie deſirous to knowe what conuerſation to vſe in earth, that he might obtaine eternall life in heauen. Our Sauiour letteth him ſee the way to obedience of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: <hi>Thou shalt not ſteale: thou shalt not kill, &amp;c.</hi> Saith the young man, If this be all I am in good caſe: all theſe haue I obſerued from my youth. Chriſt meaning to ſift him, and to ſhake him out of the ragges of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, willeth him to ſell all, and to giue to the poore, &amp;c. When he heard this, the caſe was altered, and he went away ſorie that he could not hold his poſſeſſions and Chriſt together. This young man is nowe become old
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21478:5"/>
and a grandfather of many children in theſe dayes, who will be thought to be Egles in affection to ſoare aloft, and yet are ſnailes with their houſes vpon their backes, and creepe vpon the earth.</p>
            <p>Theſe haue ſquinting eyes, with the one looking at the heauens: with the other beholding the earth: theſe be outlawes who are faithfull to no common wealth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different men in factions, who fauour no ſide: theſe be ſuch cakes as the Prophet Oſeas ſpeaketh of, baked vp v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the one ſide, and raw vpon the other, neither hote nor cold, and therefore to be ſpued out of the mouth of God.</p>
            <p>In deede they are earthly minded, but in ſhewe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly affected: their tongues and countenaunce, their wordes and lookes are holy: but their hearts and hands, their affections and actions are worldly. The marke and brand of the fleſh can not more fitly be ſet vpon any, then vpon many who carrie a zeale of holy profeſſion. Let many aske their owne hearts whether I ſay truth, and they ſhall receiue anſwer, I lye not. They muſt confeſſe, that they are trees full of leaues, but voyd of frute: dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilles couered with ſnowe, white without and foule within.</p>
            <p>The caſe of the foxe is more worth then his carkaſſe, and the profeſsion of theſe men ſomthing to be eſteemed: but the body of their behauiour is vile &amp; nothing worth. They are painted graues: in truth they be citizens of the world, though in ſhew they pretend this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this heauenly conuerſation.</p>
            <p>But the true ſeruants of God, although in infirmitie without perfection, yet in ſinceritie without diſsimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in minde and affection are heauenly, and haue their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21478:6"/>
conuerſation as citizens of Ieruſalem which is aboue: they acknowledge them ſelues to be pilgrims and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, hauing here no abiding citie, but looke for one, whoſe maker and builder is God. They are in the world, but not of the world: they vſe the world as though they vſed it not: they do eſteeme their houſes as Innes to reſt in, not as manſions to dwell in for euer: they know that all the manifold graces of God in the mind, in the bodie, without the bodie, are taken of their Maiſter, and they but ſtewards thereof.</p>
            <p>They vſe all worldly commodities as ſtaues in their hands, which they will ſet downe at the laſt ſtep of their iourney: or as oares to rowe with, which readily they will leaue when they come to the hauen where they would be. Their vnderſtanding is lightened with Gods truth: their affections are ſtrengthened by his will: their actions are reformed by his word. They looke not backe with delight to their old ſinnes, as Lots wife to Sodome, nor returne with their hearts to Egypt againe with the murmuring Iſraelites, neither wiſh they to tarrie on this ſide Iordane without the land of promiſe, as <hi>Ruben</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi> and halfe <hi>Manaſſes</hi> did: but as <hi>Daniel</hi> opened his windowes toward Ieruſalem, ſo they lift vp their eyes to heauen, and ſend thither their ſighes and grones in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, teſtifying that all their refuge is there: and lift vp their voyces with praiſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> matters go well with them, confeſſing that all good gifts come from aboue.</p>
            <p>As the Egle caſteth her bil and renueth her youth, and as the ſnake ſtrippeth of her skin and becometh ſmooth; ſo they leaue the rotten ragges of Adams corruption, and put on the innocencie of Chriſt, which is the wedding garment wherewith vnleſſe we be clothed, we ſhall be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21478:6"/>
ſhut out from the marriage feaſt. If God threaten, they tremble, if he ſhew foorth his louing countenance, they are cheered at the heart: if he teach, they giue diligent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance: if he correct, they humble them ſelues. They labor in worldly cauſes, but not with worldly affections: they giue obedience to lawfull rulers, not as to men, but as to the lieutenants of God: they walke vpon the earth with the feete of their bodies, but in their deſires, which are the feet or rather the wings of the mind, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in heauen.</p>
            <p>The workes of darkneſſe are weariſome vnto them, becauſe they are children of the light: the frutes of the fleſh are lothſome to them, becauſe God hath renued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his ſpirit: the freedom of Gods adoption is moſt ſweet vnto them, hauing eſcaped the ſlauerie of Satan.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer is purely good, they deſire it with their whole hart: what is meerely euill, they hate it with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hatred: things indifferent, which are good or euill as they are vſed or abuſed, in them they are carefull to make profit, and heedfull not to offend: in all things they firſt ſeeke the glorie of God, and next their owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>This is the narrow way that leadeth to life: this is the delight of Gods Saints in earth: this is to haue a heauenly conuerſation: which may not be thought a matter of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice or imagination, as if no ſuch were to be found, like <hi>Platoes</hi> common wealth, or <hi>Zenophons</hi> king, ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of a heauenly conuerſation.</p>
            <p>I ſayd at the firſt, that none haue it in perfection, but euerie one leſſe or more muſt haue it without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For none are perfect in this life: the brighteſt fire hath ſome ſmoke, the cleereſt water ſome mudde.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21478:7"/>The face of <hi>Venus</hi> had a mole: the moſt heauenly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hath ſome infection of the earth. <hi>Noah</hi> the ſeede of the ſecond world and the relique of the firſt, was yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken with wine: <hi>Lot</hi> was a righteous man, yet foully defiled with inceſt: <hi>Dauid</hi> a man after Gods owne heart, yet had he not ſmall ſlips but groſſe falles: <hi>Salomon</hi> a wiſe king, yet bewitched with women: <hi>Peter</hi> a great Apoſtle yet an Apoſtata for a time.</p>
            <p>But why do I vpbrayd the naked infirmities of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſeeing all fleſh hath corrupted his wayes, and none can ſay, my heart is cleane or my handes innocent. And yet God hath his flock, although it be but a litle one: and Chriſt hath his Church, his familie, although they be fewe in it. God hath his number in earth which in ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie without hypocriſie haue their conuerſacion in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Euery man may be a witneſſe to himſelfe, to whether number he belongeth, by that rule which <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> hath ſet downe in Pſal. 64. <hi>Duas ciuitates duo faciunt amores: Hieruſalem facit amor Dei: Babiloniam amor ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi. Interroget ergo ſe quiſque quid amet, &amp; inueniet vnde ſit ciuis.</hi> Two loues make two Cities: the loue of God, maketh Ieruſalem; the loue of the world, Babylon.</p>
            <p>Therefore let euerie man deale truely with his owne heart, and in euen ballances lay all his doings, putting thereto ſuch loue as he hath. If it be the loue of God, it wil lift them vp, and ſhew them to be heauenly: if the loue of the world ſet them a worke, it wil bewray their conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be of the earth. To execute iuſtice with a ſtraight hand, to cheriſh vertue, to roote vp vice, to foſter reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to baniſh ſuperſtition, to do any good, to eſchue any euill, for anie other cauſe but in loue and obedience vnto God, is not to haue an heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly but an earthly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21478:7"/>The ſpider of a drie ſlime which commeth off her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, weaueth her webbe, and ſetteth her nets to take the flie which is her foode: and many times when curiouſly ſhe hath finiſhed her worke, a blaſt of winde taketh her and it away: ſo the loue of the world cauſeth manie to wearie their bodies, trouble their wittes, breake their ſleepe, to ſet nets for commodities which are but ſmall, and by the laſt breath of our life caried away. The loue of the world which ruleth in vs by corruption of nature, and cuſtome of life, withdraweth vs from ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation as is heauenly: whereas the loue of God if it be but as a graine of muſtard ſeede, doth ſeaſon all our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and cleareth them from earthly corruption.</p>
            <p>Therfore let euery man as he groweth in yeares, ſo go forward in goodneſſe, increaſe in faith, in knowledge, in vertue, in the loue of God: decreaſe in ignorance, in infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, in vice, in the loue of the world. As our age and gray haires come on, ſo let our olde conuerſation vaniſh away, putting on the new man in holineſſe of behauiour: the nearer we come to our heauenly countrey, to wiſh and deſire it the more. For as the child in the wombe is more quick and ſtrong the nearer the time of birth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth: ſo it ſhould be with vs. For as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth, <hi>Nos ſumus in mundo vt puellus in vtero:</hi> and happie are they that are dayly more quicke and ſtrong in godlineſſe of life, that may with a good conſcience ſay as <hi>Paule</hi> doth here, Our conuerſacion or citie like behauiour is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>The cauſe which draweth vp mens hearts in deſire &amp; affection to heauen, is the ſauiour the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. The braſen ſerpent was lift vp in the wilderneſſe, that the people being ſtong might be healed &amp; liue: the ſonne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21478:8"/>
of man is lifted vpon the croſſe, lifted vp and ſet in the view of all men by the preaching of the Goſpell: and by his glorious aſcenſion into heauen, draweth all their hearts to him that looke for ſaluation in him: they feare him as their Lord, loue him as their Ieſus, reuerence him as their Chriſt: they kiſſe him as their Sauiour, that find and feele by the ſeale of Gods ſpirit, that God hath made him Chriſt, appointed him and annointed him to be a Lord and king to gouerne them, a Prieſt to ſacrifice him ſelfe for them, a Prophet to teach and inſtruct them.</p>
            <p>What greater daunger then to haue our cogitations and affections as traitors and rebelles to worke treaſon within vs, and to conſpire our deſtruction? and what happier benefite, then to haue them tamed, changed, and made pliable in obedience to an heauenly gouernment? This profite Chriſt worketh in his people, being their Lord to rule them, and this kingdome we pray for dayly to come vnto vs.</p>
            <p>What greater diſcomfort then to lye in darkneſſe, and to liue in ignorance? and what ſweeter mercie, then to haue our eyes opened, and the brightneſſe of heauenly knowledge to ſhine about vs? This commoditie our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour beſtoweth vpon vs, and is made Chriſt our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet for this end.</p>
            <p>No perill is ſo fearfull as to be out of Gods fauour, nor bleſſing ſo chearefull as to be at peace with him. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour in loue hath giuen him ſelfe for vs a ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice, and in him the Father is pleaſed with vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> was in great danger among the Lyons: yet his bodie could but be hurt, for his ſoule was comforted in that he ſuffered for the Lord: but mankind was in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable plight being iuſtly condemned body and ſoule into
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21478:8"/>
hell. Chriſt hath reached forth his hand, and drawen vs out of the iawes of the Lyon, and is become a Ieſus, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeeing as Chriſt is the mine where all theſe treaſures lye hid, the iewell houſe where all theſe pearles are heauenly gouernment, he is the Lord: heauenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, he is Chriſt a Prophet: heauenly reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he is Chriſt a Prieſt: heauenly redemption, he is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus a Sauiour. It is no maruell though the hearts of Gods children be with him, who hath in ſtore all theſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for them. The marchant hath his minde in thoſe places where his goods are, and whence he hopeth for commoditie. The husbandmans heart is in the harueſt, which is the end of his labour and the hope of his paine. Profit will carrie mens deſires verie farre, euen through the world, yea to heauen: and happie are they which venture the fartheſt, for in this life there is no true treaſure to be found.</p>
            <p>The minde of man is wider then the world, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world can fill it. Nay the mo worldly things that are heaped into it, the more it retcheth as whitlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and is more voyd and emptie. Few things will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſe the bodie: but all is not inough to ſatisfie the mind, as <hi>Philip</hi> the king of Macedonia confeſſeth of himſelfe: who in wraſtling tooke a fall vpon the ſand, and riſing, looked vpon the place, where he might ſee the print which his bodie had made to be compaſſed in a ſmall peece of earth: where the whole world was too litle for his couetous mind. For ſo he ſpeaketh of him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The ambitious man which climeth to honour, the higher he is, the higher he would be, he ſtill buildeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. <hi>Nemrods</hi> tower is too low for him, and yet it was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21478:9"/>
high 1174. paces. The pride of Lucifer which was amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the falling Angels in heauen, is now found among the ſonnes of men in the earth.</p>
            <p>The voluptuous man is like him who hath the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: the more he drinketh, the more he deſireth: he would lye deeper and longer with the ſwine in the mire.</p>
            <p>The couetous man (as the graue) neuer ſaith there is inough. Gods good giftes are without vſe buried in him. His arke and his cheſt may be filled, but his heart in the cheſt of his body can neuer be ſatisfied. Honour, profite, pleaſure, no earthly thing can content the heart of man. It is onely this Lord, this Sauiour, this Chriſt, which draweth mens hearts to heauen, and there fully ſatisfieth them.</p>
            <p>The Iſraelites in the wilderneſſe did eate Manna and dranke of the water out of the rocke, but hungred and thirſted, and died in the end. But they which are fed with the true bread that came downe from heauen, and drinke of the water of life, they ſhall neuer be more a thirſt, but ſhall haue eternall life. Chriſt Ieſus is the euerflowing &amp; ouerflowing well. Bleſſed are they that hunger &amp; thirſt for him, for they ſhall be ſatisfied in him: he is the pearle for which we muſt ſell all and buy him. He is our head, and with the ſerpent we muſt be wiſe to ſuffer loſſe in our bodies, in our goods, in our fame, in our liberties, in our liues, ſo that we keepe our head ſafe.</p>
            <p>Aeneas when Troy was won, hauing a grant (as all the citizens had) to carie away ſome one chiefe thing, which he made beſt account of, choſe, and tooke away <hi>Patrios Poenates,</hi> the gods of his countrey: preferring them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his father, his goods, or any other thing which might be of price with him. Which action of his, may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21478:9"/>
teach vs in our deſires and affections, to make choiſe of Chriſt, and lift vp our hearts to him. He requireth in the Goſpell, to be preferred before thoſe things, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be of moſt value with vs. He that doth not forſake father and mother is not worthie of me. He would not ſuffer one whom he called, to take his leaue of his friends at home, nor permit another to bury his father, a worke of humanitie and pietie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hieronimus ad Heliodorum</hi> hath a worthie iudgement agreeable to this: <hi>licet à collo paruulus pendeat infans: licet vbera quibus te nutrierat, oſtendat mater: licet in limine iaceat pater, vt te à Chriſto retardent: abijciatur infans, contemne matrem, calcandus eſt pater: ſolum eſt pietatis ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in his fuiſſe crudelem.</hi> If thy young child hang about thy necke: if thy mother ſhew her breaſts wherewith ſhe nurſed thee, if thy father lye in the doore to ſtay thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> following of Chriſt: caſt from thee thy child, contemne thy mother, tread vpon thy father: <hi>ad Chriſti vexillum vola,</hi> flie to the banner of Chriſt to be his ſouldier and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant: it is pietie to be cruell in this caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glaucus</hi> carieth the bell among all fooles for changing his golden armour for braſen harneſſe. The Iſraelites lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed Manna, and wiſhed the onions and garlicke, the groſſe diet of Egypt. The Gergeſens were more grieued for the loſſe of their ſwine, then glad of the preſence of Chriſt: nay they deſire him to depart out of their coaſts. And all the ſonnes of the earth theſe <hi>Terrigenae fratres</hi> may with the Athenians giue for their badge the graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopper, which is bred, liueth &amp; dieth in the ſame grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: ſo their whole deſire both in life and death is in earth: and as the graſhopper hath wings, but flyeth not, ſometimes ſhe hoppeth vpward a litle, but preſently falleth to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21478:10"/>
earth againe: ſo they haue ſome light, and ſhort motions to goodneſſe, but they returne to their old affections of the world, their portion is only in this life: for they loue vanitie more then truth, droſſe then gold, earth then hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the world then him that made and redeemed the world, riches that ruſteth, before treaſure that laſteth, traſh and pelfe, not true wealth which maketh happie, anie earthly vncertaintie before this Sauiour the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the onely author of all felicitie.</p>
            <p>Thoſe foules that feede groſſely neuer flie high: and they which feed their hearts with things below, can not haue their affections in heauen. The Sunne draweth out of the ſea the cleareſt water, leauing the groſſe and dregs behind, which ſome thinke is the cauſe of the ſaltneſſe of the ſea: ſo the ſonne of God draweth vp the harts of them that are pure, but leaueth below the earthly minded.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt be deare vnto vs, if the day ſtarre be riſen in our hearts, if we find in our ſoules that Chriſt is a Lord, a Ieſus, a Sauiour; if the power of theſe offices take place in our conſciences, it cannot be but our harts ſhal be with him. Gods ſpirit worketh this confeſſion in vs, that with feeling we may ſay the Lord is Ieſus, as Paule writeth, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. To ſpeake the wordes without ſence thereof is to no vſe. The parrot vttereth wordes, but knoweth no meaning: but the godly do find with ioy, that Chriſt is the way by truth to life: the ladder by which they aſcend to heauen: the good ſhepheard by whom they are ſafe: the henne vnder whoſe wings they reſt quietly. In him is their health, wealth, ioy, reſt, felicitie: he is their treaſure, and therefore their hearts are with him: whereby it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, that they long for and deſire his comming.</p>
            <p>The firſt comming of Chriſt was long wiſhed and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21478:10"/>
moſt deſired. The holy fathers who with the eye of faith a farre off ſaw that day, reioyced, as Chriſt ſpeaketh of Abraham: and when he was come, there was great glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof. The Angell telleth the ſhepheards, that he brought tidings of great ioy to all people. The ſame night that he was borne there was great light, in token of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: but at his death there was darkneſſe vpon the day, in ſigne of ſorow. The Sunne put on his mourning gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and was aſhamed to looke vpon that cruelty, which the ſonnes of men were not afrayd to commit. If that firſt comming of Chriſt was ſo ioyful, which was but meane and ſimple, alone and ſolitarie: when he came to ſtand at the barre to be iudged: when he gaue vs but the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of our ſaluation: thriſe more comfortable ſhall his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming be, which ſhalbe in glorie, attended vpon with ten thouſand of Saints and Angels: when he ſhall ſit him downe to iudge the wicked, &amp; giue full poſſeſſion of his kingdome to the elect.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall the ſheepe be gathered into the fold, neuer to be in daunger of wandering, or of the wolfe: then ſhall the corne be inned into the barne, neuer to be ſhaken with the winde or weather againe: then ſhall there be a Saboth, after which no work-day ſhal follow: then ſhall be an euerlaſting Iubilie, when all bondage ſhall ceaſe, and the choſen ſhall enter to their inheritance, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall be taken from them.</p>
            <p>The hope of this day holdeth vp the heads of Gods children in the middeſt of infinite miſeries of this life, and ſweeteneth the bitter taſt of ſundry afflictions in this world, and breedeth a ſound ioy in the hearts of them that haue eyes to ſee ſo farre. <hi>Auguſt. Pſal.</hi> 147. <hi>Quare non gaudes cum venerit iudicare te, qui venerit iudicari propter
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21478:11"/>
te?</hi> Why art thou not ioyfull of his comming to iudge thee, who came to be iudged for thee?</p>
            <p>The careleſſe carnall man hath no ſence or ſight of this day: but as the oxe is fatted in the paſture, and the bird ſingeth ſweetely, and feedeth without feare: and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly the one is carried to the ſlaughter, the other taken in the ſnare: So the worldlings are drowned in ſecuritie, and ſeldome thinke of, much leſſe wiſh for the comming of this Sauiour.</p>
            <p>Some fewe who are ſtong with ſinne, and force the wrath of God againſt them, do tremble and feare at the remembrance of this day, and wiſh it might either not be at all, or elſe be deferred: and ſome fooliſhly perſwade themſelues that it is farre, and ſay as the euill ſeruant doth in the Goſpell, my maiſter will deferre his comming.</p>
            <p>But the godly crie, Lord Ieſus come quickly: nowe they are wardes, then ſhall they come to their owne: now they are in the skirmiſh, then ſhall they be in the victorie: now they are in the tempeſtuous ſea, then ſhall they be in the quiet hauen: now in the heate of the day, then ſhall they be in the reſt of the euening: now in place they are abſent from Chriſt, though in affection they be preſent with him: then ſhall they follow him whither ſoeuer he goeth: nowe their life is hidde with Chriſt, but when Chriſt ſhall appeare, they alſo ſhall appeare with him in glorie.</p>
            <p>In the eight chapter to the Romanes and nineteenth verſe, Paule ſaith, that all the creatures of God haue a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deſire for the reuealing of the ſonnes of God: much more ſhould the ſonnes of God them ſelues deſire that day.</p>
            <p>In the fourteenth of the Reuelation, the word of God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21478:11"/>
is likened to the ſound of many waters, to the thunder, to harping with harpes, becauſe in the hearers it hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe effectes, as this particular point which now I haue in hand. For when the comming of Chriſt to iudgement is ſpoken of, to carnall men it is an idle ſound, as if Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune were mouing the ſea: to other it is terrible and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as if Iupiter threwe his thunderbolt amongſt them: theſe be wounded, but want the medicine. But to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it is ſweete muſicke, as if Apollo played vpon his harpe. I will iudge none, but the word which I ſpeake will touch euery one: our owne conſciences will accuſe vs as careleſſe, and fearfull of Chriſts comming, or excuſe vs, as ioyfull therof. Let euery one make choiſe of his companie, and ſit him downe with his owne fellowes: either with the careleſſe, who neuer thinke of it, &amp; their caſe is dangerous, vnleſſe God reuiue them: or among the fearfull, of whom there is no hope, vnleſſe God heale and cure them: or with the faithfull, who are in bleſſed ſtate, becauſe their redemption draweth neare.</p>
            <p>This is the chaunge in the ſoules of the godly, which muſt go before that other of the body, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Anima debet prius reſurgere per gratiam quam corpus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurgat ad gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> the ſoule muſt riſe againe in newneſſe of life by the grace of God before the bodie ſhall riſe to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Of the which change of the bodie I will now intreate in the ſame order as I firſt pointed it out.</p>
            <p>Our bodies they are vile, baſe, full of infirmities: and therefore in the Scriptures compared to weake &amp; meane things, to graſſe, to the flower of the field, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 40. to duſt and aſhes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.27. to houſes of clay, <hi>Iob.</hi> 4.19 to earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſes of this tabernacle, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. Our bodies when they are young, are weake twigges, when they are olde,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21478:12"/>
are doting trees, in the beſt age as veſſels of glaſſe, yea more brittle as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: for by carefull looking vnto, glaſſes are kept a long time after their death who made them and vſed them. Euerie creature liueth of his owne: but man for the maintenance of his vile bodie, hath a licence to begge, and craueth the helpe of euerie creature. The Sunne lendeth him light: the ayre breath: the water drinke: the beaſtes, birds and fiſhes, and foules feed him with their fleſh, and cloath him with their haire, wooll and skin. The rich man in the Goſpell, who was cloathed in purple, whence had he it but of the ſheepes fleece for the matter, and of the ſhell fiſh for the colour? His fine linnen, which nowe beareth all the viewe for bands like windmill ſailes, which may not vnfitly be ſo termed, becauſe mens heads are caried about with euerie wind and blaſt of vanitie: whence and what is it but the barke and as it were the skin of the line and flaxe. The ſilke wherein euen meane perſons do ruffle, is but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements of the wormes. The golde and pearles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with this bodie is attyred, are the guts and bowels of the earth: yea ſome do borrow the haire of the dead.</p>
            <p>We came naked into this world, and ſhould ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue if we had not help of the creatures, who lend vs their feathers to couer vs, as in the end naked we muſt returne to the earth. They that be come of noble houſes, borne of honorable parents, deſcended of the kings ſtocke and blood royal, yet haue their bodies vile, as Paul here mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, as ſubiect to diſeaſes, as needing all helps for health, as vnable to endure labour, heate, cold, to abide hunger, thirſt, as vnable to want ſleepe, reſt, as other men. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they that be great haue their bodies vile, much more we that be wormes and no men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21478:12"/>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> was perſwaded by flatterers, that he was the ſonne of Iupiter, a god and no man: but by want of ſleepe when he was wearie, and by ſmart of body when he was wounded, confeſſed that he was mortall as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Alexander</hi> with a proud minde ſayling vp Nilus, intending to find the ſpring thereof, which yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer could be knowen, was perſwaded by an old man to returne, who gaue him a pearle of this propertie, that being layd in ballance with anie mettall, it was to heauy, but couering it with duſt, a feather was heauier then it. By which was meant, that <hi>Alexander</hi> him ſelfe, who in his life time was too ſtrong &amp; mightie for all the world, being dead was as weake as other men. So that ſickneſſe and death, are incident to the greateſt of all: whereby is plaine, how vile and baſe our bodies are.</p>
            <p>This cutteth downe the pride of all the world, where euerie man kiſſeth his owne handes, and thinketh too well of him ſelfe for his birth, ſtrength, youth, beautie. We muſt remember that we were made of the ſlime of the earth, and muſt returne to the duſt: euen the beſt and higheſt of vs all muſt confeſſe as <hi>Iob.</hi> 17.13. The graue ſhall be my houſe: I ſhall make my bed in the darke: I ſhall ſay to corruption, thou art my father, and to the wormes, you are my ſiſter and mother.</p>
            <p>There is an old riddle, what ſhould be both the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the daughter: the anſwer is of the iſe: but it may as well be ſaid of the bodies of men which are made of the duſt, and ſhall thither returne againe.</p>
            <p>The conſideration that our bodies are vile, ſhould take away that too much curioſitie to attire and pamper the bodie: which commonly is in them that thinke too wel
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21478:13"/>
of them ſelues, deeming their bodies to be too good to be fed but with dainties, or cloathed but with coſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell. The winde may not blowe vpon them, nor the ſunne ſhine vpon them. Our beginning is baſe of the earth: our abode here is full of vncertaine proſperitie or ſundrie miſeries: our end is moſt vile. We muſt die like the beaſtes as Dauid ſaith <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.12. This is the ſtate of our bodies before they be chaunged and made like to the glorious bodie of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Some ſight of this glorie <hi>Peter</hi> ſaw when Chriſt was transfigured, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.2. His face did ſhine as the ſunne, and his clothes were white as the light.</p>
            <p>Of this Daniell ſpeaketh in the twelfe chapter &amp; third verſe. They that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament: and they that turne many to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.43. the Apoſtle ſaith, they riſe in incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in glorie, in power, a ſpirituall bodie. He that loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon Ieruſalem, as it is deſcribed in the Scriptures, ſhall ſee the houſes, gates, walles, ſtrong and faire: yet made of timber, ſtone, and ordinarie matter. But the new Ieruſalem in the Reuelation is moſt glorious, the walles of Iaſpir, the foundations of precious ſtones, the gates of pearles, the pauement of pure gold. For our capacitie the ſpirit of God doth thus ſet foorth the difference betwixt things in this life, and things in that better life. And the like difference there is in our bodies.</p>
            <p>Now they are but ſhadowes, but then they ſhall be as the ſunne: now they are ſimplemen, then they ſhall be as the Angels of God: now they are as cloudes, ſome higher ſome lower, ſome brighter ſome darker, as mens places differ in the world, but all hanging vncertainly in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21478:13"/>
aire, then ſhall they be as the ſtarres in the heauens: now they are as gold in the mine mingled with the earth, then they ſhall be purified ſeuen times in the fire: now our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are vile, then made like the glorious bodie of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Then all teares ſhall be wiped away, all infirmitie ſhall ceaſe, all deformitie ſhal haue an end. There ſhalbe health without ſickneſſe, ſtrength without weakneſſe, pleaſure without paine, youth without olde age. Reſt ſhall not be needfull, for there ſhall be no labour, there ſhall be felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with certaintie, and life without the reach and gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot of death: now our bodies are vile, then like the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodie of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Let vs not therefore be diſmayed in the ſundrie daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: nor let not our hearts faile and fall in the moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſickneſſe of the bodie, which can but laſt for a time, neither can it bring deſtruction. It may ouerthrowe the bodie into the graue, and there death ſhal haue dominion for a ſeaſon: but at the laſt our bodies ſhall be taken out of the power of death, and made like to Chriſts glorious bodie.</p>
            <p>This account the Martyrs of God haue made: <hi>Quid ſi tyrannus ſit interfector corporis mei cum Deus ſit ſuſceptor animae, &amp; erit reſtitutor corporis mei? Quid ſi membra la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret inimicus cum capillos annumeret Deus?</hi> What if the tyrant kill my bodie ſeeing that God will receiue my ſoule, and will alſo reſtore my bodie? What if the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie teare in peeces my members, ſeeing God hath num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the haires of my head? The bloodie hand of cruell tyrants may waſt and rend a ſunder the bodies of Gods people: but they ſhall be gathered together againe by the will and power of God: which two cauſes working to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, will performe a harder matter then this. For if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21478:14"/>
God were willing and not able, or of power but not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, then ſome doubt might be made of this change. But he is both willing and able to make this chaunge of our vile bodies, to make them like to the glorious bodie of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That God is willing, both authority of Scriptures and reaſon agreeing thereunto doth warrant vnto vs. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26.19. Thy dead men ſhall liue, euen with my bodie ſhall they ariſe: awake and ſing ye that ſleepe in the duſt: for thy deaw is as the deaw of herbes, and the earth ſhall caſt out her dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezech.</hi> 37.14. I wil open your graues, and bring you foorth of your ſepulchers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.28. The houre ſhall come when all they that are in the graues, ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God, and ſhall come foorth.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.14. If we beleeue that Ieſus is dead and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: euen ſo they that beleeue in Ieſus will God bring with him.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15. There is a iuſt treatiſe of this matter, and manie reaſons alledged why the dead ſhould riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Many miſchieuous inconueniences and inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient miſchiefes doe followe the denying or doubting hereof: as that Chriſt is not riſen: that Paule had prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched an vntruth: that the people had beleeued an vntruth: that the Apoſtles had bene falſe witneſſes. Againe, that their ſinnes were not taken away: that the dead are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly periſhed: that to hope in Chriſt is moſt miſerable. For <hi>fiducia Christianorum est reſurrectio mortuorum:</hi> the truſt of Chriſtians is the reſurrection of the dead, as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p>Beſides Chriſt is <hi>primitiae reſurgentium,</hi> the firſt frutes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21478:14"/>
of them that riſe againe: and by his reſurrection hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified all the elect thereunto. Whatſoeuer Adam hath loſt, Chriſt hath reſtored: but Adam loſt life, and by his ſinne brought in death, which Chriſt hath vanquiſhed in his death. Farther, the beginners in religion, when their death approched, made haſt to be baptized: not that their bodies might be waſhed cleane for the graue, but rather cleanſed againſt the happie day of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; as <hi>Epiphanius in Corinthianos</hi> expoundeth that point. Laſtly, the godly endure perſecution to no purpoſe if there be no riſing againe.</p>
            <p>The name and nature of death doth proue the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. For it is a ſleepe, and ſo named many times in the Scriptures: as 1. <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 4.13. Brethren I would not haue you ignorant concerning them that ſleepe, that you ſorrow not as they which haue no hope. <hi>Auguſt. epiſt.</hi> 120. <hi>cap.</hi> 32. <hi>Quinque virgines fatuae &amp; quinque ſapientes dormierunt, id eſt, moriebantur: mors enim in Scripturis dicitur ſomnus propter reſurrectionem velut euigilationem.</hi> The fiue fooliſh virgins and the fiue wiſe ſlept: that is, died: for death in the Scriptures is called ſleepe, and in reſpect of the reſurrection, as it were an awaking againe. Death is a ſweet ſleep without dreams as <hi>Socrates</hi> named it: not an euerlaſting ſleepe as <hi>Secundus</hi> the Philoſopher ſaid to <hi>Adrianus</hi> the Emperor. It may be called a braſen ſleep, a ſtrong &amp; a long ſleepe, for ſo <hi>Homer</hi> thinketh of it.</p>
            <p>That which Chriſt ſpake of the rulers daughter, may be truly affirmed of all them that be departed out of this life; that they are not dead, but fallen a ſleepe, and at the laſt day ſhall riſe againe. The places of buriall for this cauſe are called <hi>caemeteria,</hi> of which men would not haue ſuch care if there ſhould be no reſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21478:15"/>Olde father Iacob vpon his death bed in Egypt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his ſonne to burie him in the holy land: and Ioſeph at his death giueth commaundement to his brethren to carrie away his bones. Which deſire of theirs was part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be free from that idolatrous nation euen when they were dead: but chiefly it ſhewed the hope of this change. Tobias is commended for burying the dead: and Chriſt ſayd, that the woman who annointed his bodie to buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, ſhould be ſpoken off in all the world. The men of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes Gilead ſhewed mercie vpon Saul and Ionathan, in burying their bodies. <hi>Talia pietatis officia ad mortuorum corpora pertinent propter fidem reſurrectionis aſtruendam. Aug.</hi> 1. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei. cap.</hi> 13. Such duties of godlineſſe do appertaine to the dead, in token that we beleeue the reſurrection.</p>
            <p>The iuſtice of God requireth this, that the bodies of men, hauing bene partners in well or euill doing with the ſoule in this life, ſhould be partners in reward or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment after this life. The hand which is open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue bribes, the foote which is ſwift to ſhed blood, the tongue that ſpeaketh proud things, the eyes that behold vanitie, the eares that are open doores to let in vnchaſt talke, the minde a neſt of wicked imaginations, the head that deuiſeth miſchiefe and euill, the heart which boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in luſt and malicious reuenge: euery part with the whole which is a fellow with the ſoule in ſinning, ſhall beare companie in the puniſhment. Contrariwiſe, thoſe bodies which haue borne the heate and burthen of the day: ſhall haue part of the penie and wages.</p>
            <p>The Hebrue Doctors haue made plaine this by a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable deuiſed in this ſort: A man planted a vineyard, and hauing cauſe to go from home, was carefull to leaue ſuch
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21478:15"/>
watchmen as might keepe it ſafe from ſtrangers, and ſuch as ſhould not deceiue him them ſelues: therefore he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed two, the one was blind, but ſtrong of his limbes, the other had his ſight but was a creeple. In the abſence of their maiſter, they conferred how to deceiue him: and craftily the blind tooke the lame man vpon his backe, and got of the frute. At the returne of their Maiſter, he found out their ſubtilty, that they had ioyned their labour toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo he puniſhed them both together.</p>
            <p>Man ſtandeth of two partes: the bodie is blinde, but ſtrong to commit ſin: the ſoule hath his ſight &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but vnable to worke outward wickedneſſe: but both helpe forward to ſinne, and therefore in iuſtice muſt abide the puniſhment. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. We muſt all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of God, that euery man may receiue the things which he hath done in his bodie whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be good or euill.</p>
            <p>The infinite goodneſſe of God to his people, nor the vp heaped meaſure of his ſeueritie againſt the vngodly, could not be ſhewed, if this chaunge ſhould not be. For now the ioy of the elect and paine of the wicked, is but as a dreame to that which ſhalbe. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 61.7. For your ſhame you ſhal receiue double; euerlaſting ioy ſhalbe vnto you. Which place <hi>Lyra</hi> and the enterlined gloſſe expound of ioy of ſoule and bodie.</p>
            <p>The truth of God cannot ſtand if this chaunge ſhould not be. For he hath promiſed to raiſe vs vp at the laſt day, and that not one haire of our head ſhall periſh: <hi>Luke</hi> 14. When thou makeſt a feaſt call the poore, lame, &amp;c. who cannot reward thee, but it ſhalbe recompenced at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the iuſt. The laſt enemie that ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed is death. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. And leſt death might alleadge
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21478:16"/>
preſcription, God hath in all times of the world hindered his poſſeſſion, and taken from him the bodie of ſome, to ſhew that he had title &amp; right vnto them. As in the time of nature he tooke <hi>Enoch:</hi> in the time of the Lawe, he tooke away <hi>Helias:</hi> in the time of Chriſt, he tooke our Sauiour. To conclude this point, the authoritie of the Scriptures, the reaſons of the Apoſtle, the name of death to be ſleepe, the maner of buriall, the iuſtice, mercie and truth of God: are ſtrong chaines to binde vs to beleeue: and are ſure proppes to vphold this maine piller of our faith, that our bodies ſhall be changed. By theſe it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that God is willing as his power is anſwerable ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>God hath giuen to his creatures ſome portion of his power, whereby things are brought to paſſe which ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow out this change, which by his owne arme he will bring to paſſe.</p>
            <p>The Lyon being long abſent from his whelpes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in due time he could not find his pray, finding them dead, roareth in his caue, and reuiueth them againe. The Pellicane by her blood quickeneth her young ones. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius</hi> worthely deſcribeth the maner of the Phoenix death and birth againe out of her owne aſhes.</p>
            <p>The fire lyeth hid in the flint ſtone, yet a ſmall force will make it appeare. The ſunne ſetteth and riſeth againe: the moone waineth, and renueth her light: trees are cut downe, yet they ſpring afreſh: the herbes wither in the winter ſeaſon, but are greene againe in the ſommer time. The whole courſe of nature telleth vs that we ſhall die, and putteth vs in hope of our riſing againe. Our nayles being pared, our haire being cut off, yet they increaſe and growe againe. If the dead part of our bodie be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21478:16"/>
by the ordinarie power of God in nature: much more ſhall the bodies of men be reſtored by the mightie power of God.</p>
            <p>What if our bodies be conſumed to aſhes in the fire, dryed in ſhew to nothing in the aire, rotten to duſt in the earth, ſwallowed vp of fiſhes in the ſea, thoſe fiſhes taken and eaten of men, thoſe men deuoured of wild beaſtes, thoſe beaſts made a pray to rauenous foules: Diſperſe as farre as may be by imagination, the partes of mans body: yet ſhall this mightie power of God call them together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. <hi>Aug. de Ciuitate Dei, lib.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. <hi>Abſit vt aliquis ſinus naturae ita recipiat aliquid ſubtractum à ſenſibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, vt omnino creatoris aut lateat ſcientiam, aut effugiat potestatem.</hi> God forbid that any ſecret place ſhould be thought ſo to hide any thing remoued from our ſenſes, that it can either be kept from the knowledge of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, or auoyd his power. For this cauſe the ſea is ſayd to giue vp her dead, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20.13. becauſe the bodies that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh there, are leaſt like to be reſtored.</p>
            <p>But looke howe eaſie it is for the husbandman by his ſeruants to gather the wheate into his barne: ſo eaſie it is for God by his Angels, to bring all people before him.</p>
            <p>The potter can make a new veſſell of the ſame lumpe of clay if the firſt faſhion diſlike him: much more is God able, out of their duſt to raiſe againe our dead bodies. As the Captaine by the ſound of his trumpet doth awake his ſouldiers: ſo the trumpe ſhall blowe, and the dead ſhall riſe: for all ſhall heare that great voyce, whereof <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> thus ſpeaketh: <hi>Verè vox magna eſt quae petras ſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, monumenta frangit, vniuerſos mortuos reſurgere facit, &amp; ad iudicium ire compellit.</hi> It is ſurely a great or ſtrong voyce, that cleaueth the rockes, that breaketh tombs, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21478:17"/>
raiſeth the dead, and that draweth men to iudgement.</p>
            <p>Shall napkins be brought from Paules bodie to the ſicke, and diſeaſes depart from them: ſhall the ſhadow of Peter helpe the weake and ſicke: ſhall Elizeus thinke by ſending his ſtaffe to reuiue the Sunamites ſonne: ſhal the ſayd Elizeus bones giue life to a dead corps caſt into his graue? And ſhall not the mightie power of God change theſe vile bodies, and make them like the glorious body of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Aarons rod had leaues, bloomes and almonds: Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſtaffe was made a liuing ſerpent: Sara her dead wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be was mother to a ſonne. Theſe ſaith <hi>Epiphanius lib.</hi> 1. <hi>hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 9. are ſome tokens of the reſurrection. The graue may be the mother of the ſonnes of the reſurrection, hauing this great power of God to ſtrengthen it.</p>
            <p>The Behemoth is a huge beaſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the land: his bones are like ſtaues of braſſe, and his litle bones are like ſtaues of iron: the trees and reedes are too low to couer him: the riuer Iordan ſeemeth not enough for him to drinke. The Leuiathan is a monſtrous fiſh in the ſea: out of his mouth go ſparkes and lampes of fire: his heart is as ſtrong as the ſtone, and as hard as the neather milſtone: he eſteemeth braſſe as ſtraw, and iron as rotten wood. <hi>Iob.</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>If there be ſuch power in the creatures, farre more in the creator. Chriſt commandeth the windes and the ſea, and they obey him: he chargeth a legion of vncleane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, and they departe at his word: he wraſtleth with death and taketh a fall, and is caried priſoner into the graue, which is the ſtrongeſt hold and caſtle of death: but he burſteth his bandes, and breaketh open the gates, and taketh away the power of death, and will in the end vtterly vanquiſh it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21478:17"/>Chriſt raiſed the rulers daughter in the houſe, and the widowes ſonne carried out to be buried, and Lazarus which had lyen fower dayes in the graue. For with him it is all one to reſtore to life, them that haue bene lately or long dead. For as the beame of the eye diſcerneth in like ſpace, things that be neare and things farre off: ſo doth the power of God in this caſe. <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt.</hi> 49. vſeth this compariſon.</p>
            <p>The garments of the Iſraelites waxed not old, neither were their ſhoes worne in 40. yeares. This was done by the prouidence of God for that people: neither ſhall the bodies of men by death and corruption be ſo waſted, but the Lord by his power ſhall renew them. God can of the ſtones raiſe vp children vnto Abraham: farre more eaſie is it to raiſe our bodies againe out of their owne duſt.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible with God that a cammell or a cable be drawen through the eye of a needle: therefore death can not ſhut vp the graue ſo cloſe, but God will and can draw out thence theſe our vile bodies, and make them like the glorious bodie of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>If one Angell in one night can bring downe to death 185000. of the greateſt men in Senacheribs armie: ſhall not infinite thouſands of Angels call from death all the world, hauing this vanquiſhing power working with them?</p>
            <p>To winde vp all: it was harder for God to make wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the ribbe of man, to make man of the ſlime of the earth, to make the earth, the heauen, and all in them both and betweene them both of nothing, then to raiſe vp man out of his owne duſt: which if our eyes cannot ſee, nor our vnderſtanding conceiue, nor our reaſon reach vnto: yet our faith will apprehend it, being founded vpon the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21478:18"/>
wil of God declared in his word, and grounded vpon his power ſhewed in his workes. The want of theſe two foundations was the cauſe of this error in the Sadducees: for ſo Chriſt reproueth them. Do ye not erre, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures nor the power of God?</p>
            <p>The wiſe Athenians mocked at Paul when they heard him preach the reſurrection: and <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſayd he had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtudied him ſelfe, and by too much learning was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come mad, when he diſputed before him of the ſame matter. But the godly are not faithleſſe but beleeue, as Iob confeſſeth: I knowe that my redeemer liueth, &amp;c. and Martha ſaith of her brother: I knowe he ſhall riſe at the laſt day. For they build their beleefe vpon theſe two pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the will and power of God: not calling fleſh and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to counſell. For as <hi>Auguſtine ad Voluſianum</hi> ſaith: <hi>Si ratio quaeritur non erit mirabile: ſi exemplum poſcitur non erit ſingulare. Demus aliquid poſſe Deum quod fateamur nos non poſſe inueſtigare: tota ratio facti in talibus eſt potentia facientis:</hi> If reaſon be ſought, it will not be ſtrange: if an example be asked, it will not be ſingular. Let vs graunt that God can do ſome thing the reaſon whereof we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find out: In ſuch things the whole reaſon of the deed, is the power of the doer.</p>
            <p>The foreſight of this chaunge ſhould make vs warie to keepe cleane our bodies: ſeeing they muſt be chaunged and made like to Chriſts glorious bodie.</p>
            <p>The husbandman hath great care of that corne which is for his ſeede: our bodies are the ſeed of the reſurrection. The huſwife will keepe ſweete and faire thoſe veſſels which are for the table: our bodies are veſſels or ſhould be veſſels of ſanctification. The Church and temple of God ſhould be kept cleane and comely: our bodies are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21478:18"/>
the temples of the holy Ghoſt: therefore ſhould be heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully looked vnto.</p>
            <p>This is litle thought of, of the oppreſſour, who is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Lyons denne full of pray and rauine: or of the drunkard, who maketh him ſelfe a ſwill-tub: or of the proud man, who maketh his bodie a painted puppet: or of the luxurious man, who is a cage of vncleane birds, or rather a ſtable or a ſtye. We diſhonour God as much by abuſing our bodies, as Iehu did the temple of Baal, who made it an houſe of the vileſt vſe. God neuer tooke plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with his Temple of Ieruſalem after it was defiled by the Babylonians, but burnt it downe with fire: and he hath in ſtore a more fearfull fire if we abuſe our bodies.</p>
            <p>Therefore let vs be carefull to vſe well theſe crackt and brittle veſſels, for that they muſt be in better caſe: now vile, but ſhall be changed, and made like the glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt: and ſhall be vnited to the ſoules, and receiue that bleſſed inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which God the Father of old hath prepared, God the Sonne of late hath purchaſed, God the holy Ghoſt doth dayly ſeale in the hearts of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. To which three perſons, one true and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing God, be all honor, glorie and praiſe both now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
